Thomas, T. mss., 1976-1990 LMC 2692
Lilly Library
Thomas, T. mss.
1976-1990
Lilly Library
Thomas, Trevor, 1907-1993
LMC 2692
1 Box 1 standard
The Thomas, T. mss., ca. 1976–1990, consist of the papers of Trevor Thomas, the neighbor of Sylvia Plath and the last person to see her alive. The collection contains materials relating to Thomas' memoir of Plath as well as documents from Ted Hughes' libel suit against him.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Trevor Thomas, 1907-1993, was an art historian and former Director of the Leicester Museum and Art Gallery. He was also the last person to see poet Sylvia Plath alive.
Thomas was born in Ynysddu, Gwent in 1907. He served as Curator and then Director of the Leicester Museum and Art Gallery from 1940-1946, during which time he was instrumental in building the museum's collection of German expressionist art. Like his colleague Sir Kenneth Clark at the National Gallery, Thomas organized educational and social programming at the museum to provide the public with entertainment and keep up morale in spite of the war. In 1944 he arranged "Mid-European Art," an exhibition of German expressionist art, strategically sponsored by the respected anti-Nazi Free German League of Culture.The artworks had been purchased from German emigres Tekla Hess, widow of Jewish shoe manufacturer and art collector Alfred Hess, and her son Hans, who fled Germany only to be detained by the British as an enemy alien and put to work as a farm laborer near Loughborough. Thomas arranged to have Hans Hess appointed as an Art Assistant at Leicester Museum for the exhibition; Hans would go on to become Keeper of Art at York City Art Gallery.
However, in July 1946, Thomas was accused of public indecency (i.e., homosexuality) after a policeman witnessed him and another man "looking towards each other in a suspicious way" in a public lavatory. Despite receiving a character testimonial from Sir Kenneth Clark, who expected Thomas to succeed him as Director of the National Gallery, Thomas lost his career at the Leicester Museum and in the museum field more generally. Thomas would go on to work as Programme Specialist for Education through the Arts at UNESCO (1949-56) and as professor of art history at the State University of New York and the University of Buffalo, among other positions.
In 1963, Thomas lived in the flat below Sylvia Plath's on Fitzroy Road in London. He was the last person to see her alive before she committed suicide.
Thomas published a memoir about his time as Plath's neighbor, Sylvia Plath: Last Encounters (1989). He was subsequently sued for libel by Plath's widower, British poet laureate Ted Hughes, for asserting that Hughes attended a "high-spirited and boisterous party" the day of Plath's funeral. The suit was withdrawn after Thomas apologized for the assertion and agreed to destroy copies of his book.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Legal, II. Correspondence, III. Writings, and 2 folders: Thomas' biography and Clippings.
Scope and Content Note
The Thomas, T. mss., ca. 1976–1990, consist of the correspondence, writings, legal depositions, poetry, typescript of his autobiography, and poetry of Trevor Thomas, b. South Wales, 1907. The collection includes correspondence between Thomas and Aurelia Plath following her daughter's suicide; correspondence with Linda Wagner–Martin, a biographer of Plath, including a typescript copy of parts of her book and an inscribed hard copy of the published text, Sylvia Plath: A Biography. It also includes legal documents, news clippings, and testimony regarding Ted Hughes suit against Mr. Thomas for aggravated libel for comments made by Thomas in his self-published memoir, Sylvia Plath: Last Encounters.
I. Legal contains documents from the Hughes v. Thomas case. II. Correspondence includes the letters between Thomas and various people, including Aurelia Plath, Linda Wagner-Martin, and Clarissa Roche. III. Writings includes various writings regarding Sylvia Plath and Thomas' own poetry.
Related Material
See Plath, mss. I-X and Wagner-Martin, mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2009
Thomas, Trevor, 1907-; Plath, Sylvia; Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998; Plath, Aurelia Schober; Wagner-Martin, Linda
- I. Legal
  - 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990 (Box 1)
  - Hughes v. Thomas - Statement of Claim, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Hughes v. Thomas - Statement of Defence, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Hughes v. Thomas - Writ of Summons, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Hughes v. Thomas - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- II. Correspondence
  - Plath, Aurelia (Box 1)
  - Roche, Clarissa (Box 1)
  - Wagner-Martin, Linda (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- III. Writings
  - "Who Was Sylvia? Version 1 (Box 1)
  - "Who Was Sylvia? Version 2 (Box 1)
  - "Who Was Sylvia? Version 3 (Box 1)
  - Sylvia Plath: Last Encounters (Box 1)
  - More Than One Life (Box 1)
  - Poems (Box 1)
- Thomas' biography (Box 1)
- Clippings (Box 1)